A Guide to the Records of the Office of the President of James Madison University, 1951-2001
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Office of the President of James Madison University 1951-2001
The Library of Virginia
44225
10 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and other protected information is considered confidential and restricted from public access for 75 years. It may be necessary for an archivist to review any unprocessed, modern record collections (those collections less than 75 years old) that may contain confidential information before the records can be used by patrons for research purposes or before any copies of records can be made for patrons. If you are planning to use these records, please contact Archives Reference Services for more details before planning your research trip.
If a request for copies is made for material containing confidential information, it is understood that this information will be redacted from the copies, if it is possible to do so. If redaction is not possible, the records will be withheld. Researchers must also agree that no direct or indirect contact will be made with the individuals to whom any personal or confidential information relates. Improper use and/or re-disclosure of privacy protected information is a breach of confidentiality which could result in the loss of access to the archival collections housed and maintained by The Library of Virginia, and could result in legal penalties (Code of Virginia, 18.2-186.3).
Acquisition Information
James Madison University, Office of the President, Records, Michele White, University Registrar, James Madison University, MSC 3528, Harrisonburg, VA 22807, transferred 7 April 2009 and accessioned 23 April 2009.
Historical Information
James Madison University is a public comprehensive university that offers bachelor's, master's, and doctoral degrees, with a primary focus on undergraduate studies. The university is located in Harrisonburg in the Shenandoah Valley of Virginia. It was established by the General Assembly in March 1908 as the State Normal and Industrial School for Women at Harrisonburg, with Julian Ashby Burruss as its first president. The school changed name to the State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg in 1914 and the school received authorization to grant bachelor's degrees in 1916. The school changed names several more times, to the State Teachers College at Harrisonburg in 1924 and then to Madison College in 1938 in honor of James Madison, fourth President of the United States. The college admitted men in 1946 and had it's final name change occured in 1977 when it adopted it's current name, James Madison University.
Past Presidents include: Dr. G. Tyler Miller, 1949-1970; Dr. Ronald E. Carrier, 1971-1998; and Dr. Linwood H. Rose, 1998-present.
Scope and Content
Contains correspondence, subject files and reports created and collected by the Office of the Presidnet of James Madison University. The files relate mostly to the university departments, committees, faculty and university oversight groups (State Council of Higher Education for Virginia). Files in this collection also document the activities between the university and various state agencies such as the Office of the Governor, Secretary of Education and the Virginia Department of Education.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1951-2001
Contents List
- I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1951-2001., Extent: 10 cubic feet (10 boxes). (Box 1-10)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject headings and subdivided by folder titles
  - Academic Affairs, 1993-1998
    - Organization Membership (Box 1)
    - General Files-SURA (Box 1)
    - National Center for Higher Education Management Systems (NCHEMS) (Box 1)
    - Post-Tenure Review (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs - Fellowships (Box 1)
    - Faculty Senate (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs Assessment (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, Committee Reports, Instr. Faculty Roles (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, VP Office (Box 1)
    - AAVP (Box 1)
    - National Science Foundation (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, Military Science, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Virginia Army National Guard/JMU, Agreement, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Integrated Learning Resources, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
    - Academic Advising, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
    - College of Business, COB Departments, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Fine Arts and Communication, WMRA, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
    - College of Arts and Letters, Center for the Arts, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, Task Force on Science and Math, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, Joint Law Library Committee, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, NCATE, 1992 and 1995 (Box 1)
    - College of Education and Psychology, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, Public Higher Education, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, Vice President's Office, General Education, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Academic Affairs, Faculty Assistance Awards, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
    - Graduate School, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Academic Affairs, College of Science and Math, 1993-1998
    - Environmental Science Major (Box 1)
    - College of Letters and Sciences, Life Science Museum (Box 1)
    - College of Health Sciences (Box 1)
    - College of Health and Human Services, Nursing Department (Box 1)
    - College of Science and Math (Box 1)
  - Academic Affairs, Memos and Correspondence, 1998-2000
    - Academic Affairs, 1998 (Box 1)
    - College of Arts and Letters, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - College of Business (Academic Affairs),1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - College of Education and Psychology,1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - CISAT (Academic Affairs), 1996-2000 (Box 1)
    - College of Science and Mathematics, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Academic Affairs, Psychology Doctoral Program, 1994-1996
    - Academic Affairs, Doctoral Programs, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Affairs, 1973-1981
    - Southern Association of College and Secondary Schools, 1960 Meeting (Box 4)
  - Audit and Management Review, 1991-1995
    - Records (Box 4)
  - CISAT, 1993-1997
    - JMU/Coors Research Park (Box 2)
    - Economic Development (Box 2)
    - CISAT Correspondence (Box 2)
    - CISAT Bridge (Box 2)
    - CISAT - Provost (Box 2)
    - CISAT-Telecommunications (Box 2)
    - CISAT-JMU-JC Penny Research (Box 2)
    - CISAT-Governor's School Program (Box 2)
    - CISAT-Health Sciences (Box 2)
    - Land Mine Project, Essex (Box 2)
  - CISAT SCHEV Proposal, 1992
    - Records (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (via Assistant to President), 1998-1999
    - Records (Box 1)
  - Faculty Correspondence, 1989-1992
    - Faculty Correspondence, 1989-1992, other (Box 4)
    - Faculty Correspondence, 1989-1992, concerns (Box 4)
    - Faculty Correspondence, 1989-1992, general (Box 4)
  - President's General Correspondence, 1971-1984
    - Records (Box 4)
  - REC Correspondence, 1998-1999
    - Correspondence, Students, 1998-1999 (partial) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, General, 1998-1999 (partial) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, Faculty/Staff, 1998-1999 (REC) (Box 4)
  - Governor's Office Correspondence, 1964-1972
    - Records (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - Attorney General, 1951-1969 (Box 7)
    - Attorney General, 1970-1984 (Box 7)
    - Attorney General, 1978 (music copyrights) (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1995-1996
    - Records (Box 8)
  - Correspondence Faculty/Staff, 1995-1996
    - Records (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1995-1996
    - Students (A-J) (Box 8)
    - Students (K-Z) (Box 8)
  - Student Recommendations, 1993-1994
    - Records (Box 2)
  - [Student] Recommendations, 1995-1996
    - Records (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, Faculty/Staff, 1994-1995
    - Records (Box 8)
  - Student Correspondence, 1994-1995
    - Records (Box 8)
  - General Correspondence, 1994-1995
    - Records (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1998
    - General, A-J (Box 9)
    - General, K-Z (Box 9)
    - Faculty/Staff (Box 9)
    - Student (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997
    - Student Correspondence (A-I) (Box 10)
    - Student Correspondence (J-Z) (Box 10)
    - General/VIP Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Faculty/Staff Correspondence (Box 10)
  - Council of Presidents, 1965-1969
    - Records (Box 2)
  - Electricity Cost Commission, 1975
    - Charge to the Commission (Box 7)
    - Reports (Box 7)
    - News Clippings (Box 7)
  - Energy Advisory Council, 1978-1979
    - Energy Advisory Panel, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Energy Advisory Council, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Federal Agencies Correspondence, 1968-1983
    - U.S. Departmen of State, Exchange-Visitor Program (Box 4)
    - Other Federal Agencies, Current Fiscal Year (Box 4)
    - Other Federal Agencies, Current Fiscal Year (Box 4)
  - Harrisonburg Revitalization, 1993-1997
    - Downtown Revitalization (Box 2)
    - General Files, Harrisonburg (Box 2)
    - Downtown Revitalization (Box 2)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Records (Box 2)
  - Harrisonburg/Rockingham Issues
    - Records, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Institutional Effectiveness
    - Records, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - Institutional Research
    - Records, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
    - Honor Council, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
    - Human Resources, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate Athletics
    - Records, 1992-1997
  - International Education and Programs, 1991-1997
    - Studies Abroad, Madison House, London, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Agrentina and Brazil, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Chile, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Salamanca, 1998 (Box 4)
    - International Education, Correspondence, 1991-1996 (Box 4)
    - International Education, Japan/China, 1993-1997 (Box 4)
    - Overseas School Board Members - Assessment Program, 1995 (Box 4)
    - International Education, Italy, 1993-1995 (Box 4)
    - Marymount International School, 1994 (Box 4)
    - International Education, 1994-1998 (Box 4)
  - Land Advisory Committee
    - Records, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - Records, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Legislative Branch
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Letters and Information, 1992-1998 (Box 5)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Division of Legislative Services, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission, 1991-1994 (Box 5)
    - General Assembly, 1996 (Box 7)
    - General Assembly, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Files
    - Coalition for Virginia's Future, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Campaign for Education Policy Committee (Box 1)
    - International Education, 1997-2000 (Box 1)
    - Tuition Contracts, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Governance Study, 1999 (Box 1)
    - General Assembly, 1999 (Box 1)
  - President's Events
    - Records, 1994-1997 (Box 4)
  - SACS - 1960 Meeting
    - A.I.A.W. (Box 5)
    - Athletic Affairs (Box 5)
  - Secretary of Administration
    - Department of Personnel and Training (Box 5)
  - Secretary of Administration and Finance, 1991-1997
    - Bonds (Box 9)
    - Decentralized Administrative Authority (Box 9)
    - VP Office - Decentralization (Box 9)
    - Administrative Services, Police and Safety (Box 9)
    - VP - Higher Education Budget (Box 9)
    - Merit Pay (Box 9)
    - Employee Relations and Training, Grievance Procedures (Box 9)
    - Finance, Compliance (Box 9)
    - Relations - Lag Pay (Box 9)
    - Faculty Salary Equity Study (Box 9)
    - Newman Lake - Mud Problem (Box 9)
    - Physical Plant (Box 9)
    - Information Technology, Comput. And Info Tech - Long Range Plans (Box 9)
    - Resource Planning and Policy, Salary Study (Box 9)
  - Secretary of Administration and Finance, Capital Projects, 1991-1997
    - Vice-President's Office, Capital Projects (Box 9)
    - Resource Planning (Box 9)
    - Institutional Research (Box 9)
    - Resource Planning - Budget (Box 9)
  - Secretary of Education
    - Enrollment Projections, 1993-1997 (Box 5)
    - Eisenhower Grant (Box 5)
    - Funds for Excellence Minigrant, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Dormitory System Revenue Bonds, Pricing Information, Wheat First Securities, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Dormitory System Revenue Bonds, Pricing Information, Wheat First Securities, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Equipment Trust Fund, 1986-1988 (Box 5)
    - State Council's Recommendations on Auxiliary Enterprises, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Virginia Plan (Box 5)
    - Virginia Plan, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Supercomputer Task Force, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Secretary of Finance
    - Decentralization Pilot Programs, 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Department of the State Internal Auditor, 1992-1996 (Box 5)
    - Secretary of Finance, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Department of Planning and Budget, 1990-1997 (Box 5)
  - State Agencies
    - Governor's Office, 1978-1983 (Box 3)
    - Governor's Office - ADP Policy Board for Higher Education, 1975-1983 (Box 3)
    - Secretary of Education, 1976-1982 (Box 3)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 1956-1970 (Box 3)
    - Governor's Office, IBM Computer Equipment, 1969-1978 (Box 3)
    - Governor's Management Study Commission, 1970-1977 (Box 3)
    - Governor's Regulatory Reform Advisory Board, Fall 1982 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Information Technoloyg, 1985-1988 (Box 3)
    - Dept. Of Personnel and Training, 1985-1988 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of General Services, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Military Affairs, 1987 (Box 3)
    - DMV, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Accounts, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Treasury, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Planning and Budget, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Personnel, 1958-1977 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Highways, 1956-1983 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Purchases and Supply, 1949-1984 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Commerce, 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - Office of the Governor, 1984-1989 (Box 3)
    - Chief of Staff, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Secretary of Finance, 1984-1989 (Box 3)
    - Secretary of Education, 1985-1989 (Box 3)
    - Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1985-1988 (Box 3)
    - Attorney General, 1984-1989 (Box 3)
    - Senate, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
    - House of Delegates, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
    - VRS, 1954-1964, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Leg. Services, 1954-1977 (Box 3)
    - ABC Board, 1968-1974 (Box 3)
    - Commission on the Aging, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Commission on Constitutional Revision, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Office of the Comptroller, 1986-1988 (Box 3)
    - Office of Civic Rights, Region III, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 1988 (Box 3)
    - SCC, 1985 (Box 3)
    - World Trade, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - SCHEV, 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - 1986-1988 Budget Target (Box 3)
    - College of Business Building, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Funds for Excellence-SCHEV, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - Capital Outlay, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Virginia Public Telecomm Council, 1974-1983 (Box 5)
    - Virginia Resource Use Council Ed. Council, 1964-1972 (Box 5)
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Art, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
    - Comptroller, 1973-1981 (Box 5)
    - Adv. Council of Va. Community Service and Cont. Ed. Program, 1966-1970 (Box 5)
    - Secretary of Education, 1990-1997 (Box 5)
    - Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Secretary of Economic Development, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Secretary of Administration, 1988-1991 (Box 5)
    - Attorney General, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
    - Office of the Governor, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
    - Attorney General, 1992-1997 (Box 5)
    - Sec. of Transportation, DMV, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Office of Lt. Governor, 1992-1995 (Box 5)
    - Office of the Governor, Correspondence, General, 1993-1998 (Box 5)
    - Office of the Governor, Economic Concerns, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
    - Office of the Governor, Governor's Commission on Government Reform, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Transportation Committee, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - Higher Ed. Study Comm., 1964-1966 (Box 7)
    - Comm. On Public Ed., 1958-1961 (Box 7)
    - Industrial Facilities Financing Study Commission, 1972-1975 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1954-1977 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1982 (Box 7)
    - Division of the Budget, 1970-1982 (Box 7)
    - General Assembly, 1978-1982 (Box 7)
  - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV)
    - SCHEV Director, 1993-1998 (Box 5)
    - SCHEV Director, 1989-1993 (Box 5)
    - Records, 1993-1998 (Box 5)
    - Records, 1969-1974 (Box 6)
    - Records, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
    - GPAC Committee, 1968-1973 (Box 6)
    - GPAC Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 6)
    - GPAC Committee, 1976-1981 (Box 6)
  - State Department of Education, 1962-1984
    - Correspondence with Supt and Assistant Supt., 1967-1984 (Box 6)
    - Administration and Finance, 1965-1982 (Box 6)
    - Superintendents' Memos (Box 6)
    - Division of Vocational Education, Home Economics-Loving, 1962-1977 (Box 6)
    - Division of Teacher Ed. and Cert. (Brooks) (Box 6)
    - Correspondence with Other Staff Members, 1965-1984 (Box 6)
    - Continuing File - Rulings, etc. (Box 6)
  - Stone Commission on Higher Education
    - Records, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Student Affairs, 1992-1997
    - Health Center (Box 10)
    - Admissions Correspondence (Box 10)
    - JMU Aids Policy (Box 10)
    - Student Affairs (Box 10)
    - Admissions, General Admission Guidelines (Box 10)
    - Admissions - Strategic Enrollment Management (Box 10)
    - Career Services (Box 10)
    - Financial Aid, Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Student Activities, Greek Organizations (Box 10)
    - Student Activities, Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Student Activities (Box 10)
    - JMU Residence Life (Box 10)
    - SGA (Box 10)
    - Student Success Center (Box 10)
  - University Advancement-Development, 1992-1997
    - JMU Foundation (Box 10)
    - Alumni Relations (Box 10)
    - Founders Day, 1997 (Box 10)
    - VP Office, Fundraising (Box 10)
    - Vice President's Office (Box 10)
    - VP Development (Search), 1998 (Box 10)
    - External Programs (Box 10)
    - DWT (Box 10)
  - University Committees, 1976-1977
    - Administrative Affairs, Business Affairs Evaluation Committee (Fall, 1976) (Box 2)
    - Continuing Education Evaluation Committee, January 1976 (Box 2)
    - Graduate School Evaluation Committee, January 1976 (Box 2)
    - Computer Center Evaluation Committee, January 1976 (Box 2)
    - Library Evaluation Committee, February 1976 (Box 2)
    - Public Affairs Evaluation Committee, January 1976 (Box 2)
    - Student Affairs Evaluation Committee, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Virginia Commission on Higher Education, Facilities
    - Records, 1965-1970 (Box 6)